here it goes hey what's up guys my name
is the chero and welcome back to my C++
Series so today possibly the most
important episode in this entire series
we're going to talk about pointers and
unfortunately pointers are an area that
a lot of people struggle with so I just
really want to say don't worry don't
overthink it pointers are actually
really simple and I also want to mention
that today we'll be talking about raw
pointers not smart pointers if you don't
know what smart pointers are don't worry
about that we'll get into that in the
future computers deal with memory memory
is everything to a computer if I had to
name the single most important thing in
programming it would probably be Memory
when you write an application and you
launch it that entire application gets
loaded into memory all of the
instructions that tell the computer what
to do in the code that you've written
all of that gets loaded into memory
that's how the CPU can actually access
your program and start executing its
instructions when you create a variable
when you load in data from disk
everything gets stored in memory there
is nothing you can do if you do not have
memory and pointers are extremely
important for managing and manipulating
that memory so what are Pointers I'm
probably going to end up saying this
multiple times throughout the course of
this video a pointer is an integer a
number which stores a memory address
that is all that it is I don't want to
get too deep into how memory actually
works in a computer I might save that
for another video but simply put your
memory inside your your computer is just
like one Big Blob it's like one big line
that's all it is picture one straight if
if your entire city that you live in
just had a single Street and there was a
start and there was an end and then you
had a bunch of houses there were no
houses across the road let's just say
there's just a street and there's like a
row of houses that is what memory is in
a computer it's just a linear
one-dimensional line and every house on
that street is going to have a number an
address so to bring that metaphor back
to computers picture that every house on
that street that has an address is a
bite it is one bite of data we obviously
need a way to be able to address all of
those bites all those houses on our
street because for example let's say
someone orders something online and
wants to have it delivered it needs to
be delivered into the right house or or
maybe someone's sending something
they're sending something away from
their house either way you need to be
able to read and write from memory from
those bites of memory from those houses
so a pointer is that address it's the
address that tells us where that house
is where that specific bite of memory is
and that's extremely important because
pretty much everything we do in our code
is going to be reading or writing from
and to memory now of course it's
perfectly possible for you in C++ to
write an application that does not use
pointers that's you you can do that you
don't necessarily need to use pointers
however they are an extremely useful
tool because as I just mentioned memory
is probably the single most important
thing you have the single most important
resource that your computer can provide
to you it's used for everything and
being able to have more control over
that memory is vital all right
anyway to
reiterate a pointer is just an address
it is an integer which holds a memory
address that is all that it is forget
types right types have nothing to do
with any of that types are just some
kind of fiction that we've created to
make our lives easier it doesn't matter
if you have an INT pointer or maybe you
have an entity class and you have an
entity pointer it doesn't matter types
types are completely meaningless right a
pointer for all types is just that
integer that holds a memory address
that's all that it is let's jump in and
take a look at some examples okay so
here in Visual Studio I've got an
extremely simple project it's just one
source file everything that you see on
the screen is the complete code that
I've got written so let's go ahead and
create a pointer we're going to create
the purest of pointers because it's
going to be something called a void
pointer void basically means that it's
completely typeless remember remember I
said that a pointer is just an address
it's just an integer which holds an
address in memory so it doesn't need a
type if we give a pointer a type we're
just saying that the data at that
address is presumed to be the type that
we give it right it doesn't mean
anything apart from that it's just
something that we can write to make our
lives easier syntactically like in the
actual source code to make our lives
easier we can use types with pointers
but again a type does not change what a
pointer is a pointer is just a memory
address it's it's just an integer so a
void pointer means that we do not care
right now in our source code what type
this actual data is because we just want
to really hold an address so let's go
ahead I'll call it PTR or pointer for
short and I'll set it equal to zero so
what is zero we've given this pointer a
memory address of zero what does that
mean well zero isn't actually a valid
memory address memory addresses do not
go all the way down to zero zero is
invalid and what that means is that this
pointer is not valid being not valid is
a perfect acceptable state for a pointer
but all I'm saying here is that zero is
not a valid memory address we can't read
from or write to a memory address of
zero if we try and do that our program
will crash so zero means null and we can
actually also write it like this which
is actually just a hash Define if you
look up what that null actually is you
can see it's just a hash Define for Z so
it's the same as if we wrote zero or we
can use a C++ keyword called null
pointer this was introduced in C++ 11 so
awesome we've made our first pointer it
is completely typeless and it has the
memory address of zero completely
useless but it's a pointer and this is
probably the simplest pointer you could
write let's do something a little bit
more useful let's create an integer so
I'm going to create a variable I'm going
to call it V and I'm going to set it
equal to a it's going to be an integer
now this is just a normal integer but of
course every variable we create has a
memory address because we need a place
to store that variable so what if I want
to find out what the memory address of
that variable is so where are you in
memory I can do that by using the
Ampersand operator so if I use an
ampersand in front of an existing
variable like this we're essentially
asking this variable hey what is your
memory address and then of course we're
taking the memory address of that
variable and in this case assigning it
to a new variable called pointer and
that's it we've now got the memory
address of our variable and we're
storing it in another variable which is
a pointer I'm going to put a break point
on this line of code and hit F5 to run
and debug my application so right now if
I take a look at what we've got we've
got a variable you can see if I hover my
mouse over it it has the value of eight
and if I hover my mouse over a pointer
it has a slightly different value which
is presented to us in heximal format but
it is as you can see still just a number
it's an integer so what that pointer
variable is holding now is the memory
address of that VAR variable and that's
all it is that number that you see there
a0f b64 that is where in memory we are
storing our integer variable and in fact
what I can do is I can grab this I can
copy it I can hit debug Windows memory
memory 1 so what this view is showing
now is all of the memory inside our
application I'm going to paste in that
value I'm just going to get rid of that
pointer at the beginning
there and then I'm going to hit enter
and check this out we are taken to this
memory address we know an integer is
four bytes of data and look at that it
has the value a we're looking at our
computer's memory right now and we can
see that at that memory address we have
the value eight because we created that
variable and we set its value to eight
all right fantastic so that's really I
mean on a basic level that's all there
is to it everything else builds from
this if you know this much and you're
following me and your understanding
that's there's no magic behind it that's
how pointers work a pointer is a
variable which holds an address an
integer a pointer is like any other
variable it's just that instead of
holding a value such as a it's holding a
memory address which a memory address is
also a value it's also an integer now
how big that integer is how big that
pointer is depends on a lot of things it
could be a 32-bit integer it could be a
64-bit integer it could be a 16bit
integer doesn't matter right the point
is it is an integer and that is all it's
ever going to be if I go back to my code
here and I change this to be an INT
pointer I'm not actually changing
anything if I run my application again
you'll see it's not going to be any
different if I go ahead and I copy that
value I'll copy the value I'll paste it
into my memory View and I'll hit enter
you can see it's still set to eight I
can go back here I could make this a
completely different type such as a
double of course it's going to give me
an error this time because the compiler
is going to warn against that I can just
cast it to a double though doesn't
matter I can I'm going to run my code
again I'm going to look at the value I'm
going to copy the value I'm going to
paste it over here and get rid of all
this other junk at the end hit enter and
look at that it takes me to that place
in memory where I'm storing my data and
there are four byes there that have the
value eight types do not matter types
are useful for manipulation of that
memory so if I want to read and write to
that memory types can help me out
because the compiler will know for
example that an integer is supposed to
be 4 bytes so when I try and set a value
there it will set four bytes of memory
But ultimately types are completely
meaningless and in future videos we're
going to take a look at that even more
deeply but for now just don't worry
about types all right so let's go back
to having our void pointer right why
wouldn't you always use a void pointer
well suppose that I wanted to get access
to my I've got a pointer which is
pointing to that data however now I want
to actually write to or read from that
data so that variable is holding the
value eight I want to change that how do
I change that how do I I've got I know
where the data is but how do I get
access to it that's where D referencing
comes in so we've gone from a VAR to a
pointer to VAR but how do I come back to
that VAR well you can do that by
sticking an asterisk at the front of
your pointer so in other words if I
write this I'm actually de referencing
that pointer which means that I'm now
accessing the data I can either read
from or write to that data so I could
for example write the value 10 in here
however if I try and do that you'll see
that I'm actually getting an error why
because we've said that point this
pointer is a void pointer which means
that I mean how how is the computer
possibly going to write the value 10
into a void pointer it doesn't know what
it is is that 10 a short which is a 2 by
integer is it an INT which is a 4 by
integer is it a long long which is an 8
by integer we don't know how many how
many bites of data should this write
right we've just said it's 10 but 10
could mean anything really that's where
types come in we need to tell the
compiler actually know this is an
integer so I expect you to write four
bytes in please so let's just go ahead
and change this to int and now of course
we've told the compiler this is an
integer we've told the compiler the
compiler hasn't been like yeah this is
this is correct we've told the compiler
if we make a mistake if we say this is
actually a double we could be in trouble
if I then output the value of VAR which
as you note is my original variable
you'll see that the value that I get is
10 Okay so we've successfully changed it
from A8 to to 10 and if we go ahead and
we set another break point over here and
run our program I'm going to come down
here into watch and actually put in that
pointer and then I'm just going to drag
the value all the way up here so that we
go to that spot of memory you'll see
that at that memory we're storing eight
if I hit F10 to advance my program one
line You'll see that now it's changed to
0 a a of course is hexadecimal for 10 so
you can see that by dereferencing a
pointer and writing to it I'm basically
accessing that data in this case I'm
writing to the data at that memory
address all right cool so you should now
know how pointers work that's really all
there is to them a pointer just points
to a location in memory some people say
that it points to a block of memory
although this isn't really accurate
because we don't know how big that block
of memory is in this case it's 4 bytes
sure cuz we've created an integer and an
integer is four bytes of memory so we do
have a pointer that is pointing to
essentially a block of four byes however
there's nothing in the actual pointer
which says how big the memory is when we
create arrays and all that it does kind
of keep track of the size I'm not going
to talk about that but simply put we
don't know how big the pointer is we
don't know how much data it's holding
because it's not holding data right a
pointer is just an integer which is a
memory
address that's it now so far we've been
directly creating data on the stack if I
create a variable like this we're
creating it in the stack portion of our
memory I'm going to be talking about the
stack and the Heap and all of that in a
later video there might be like an
annotation or something on the screen if
I've already made that video so go ahead
and check that out if you want more
details but what I could do is create a
variable on the Heap or in other words I
could ask our computer hey I want you to
allocate some memory for me and I want
it to be a certain size so what I could
do for now is use a Char star now we
know we know that a Char is one bite
right so when I ask something like this
I I'll call it a buffer and I'll set it
equal to a new Char of size eight what
I'm really asking for is 8 bytes of
memory so this has allocated 8 bytes of
memory for us and is returning a pointer
to the beginning of that block of memory
I could then use a function called
memset which basically fills the block
of memory with data that we specify it
takes in a pointer which is going to be
the pointer to the beginning of the
block of memory it's going to take in a
value such as zero and then it's going
to taken aside so how many bytes should
it fill in this case we know that we
have eight bytes let's run this program
I'm going to take this now you'll see
that this has the memory address over
here now you already know how memory
addresses work and all that so I'm just
going to type the actual variable name
buffer up here and hit enter and you'll
see that look at this we've got eight
bytes of memory in a row of course that
are all set to zero because that's what
we've done with our M set in this case
because we use the new keyword and this
data is actually Heap allocated we
should also delete the data when we're
done with it and we can do that just by
typing in delete we know it's an array
we use the array operator to allocate it
so we should use the delete keyword with
the array operator
and then delete that buffer if we were
being super nice however our program
does finish here anyway the point of
this example was just again to reiterate
that this is a pointer we've said here
that we want to allocate eight chars a
Char is one bite so Thus We've allocated
eight bytes and we're storing a pointer
to the beginning of that data one more
thing that I want to mention is the
pointers themselves are just variables
and those pointers those variables are
also stored in memory that's where we
can get things like double pointers or
triple pointers or basically pointers
two pointers how does all that work
right well you just go down a level and
you're basically just saying I now have
a pointer which points to my pointer so
I now have a variable which is storing
the memory address that's pointing to
another variable which is storing a
memory address simple right so in this
example with my buffer I could create a
double pointer right this means it's a
pointer to a pointer I'm going to call
it PCR and I'm going to set it equal to
the memory address of buffer so now this
is where it gets interesting I'm just
going to move this break point up here
because I don't want to be deleting the
data just yet let's take a look at this
slowly this is the value of pointer I'm
going to take that I'm going to copy it
in here right now you can see that over
here we've got B8 F1 02 and 0 four byes
I know that this pointer is going to be
4 bytes of memory because I'm running a
32-bit application and in a 32-bit
application a memory address is 32 bits
more on that in another video now
because of the endianness of this
computer it's actually in reverse order
so if I paste this in here we actually
have to rearrange it so that it says 0 0
02 F1 and then B8 at the end like that
if I hit enter look at that I'm taken to
the memory which stores this buffer of
zeros okay that's it pointers to
pointers sorted right really simple
stuff so that's it I could keep talking
about this all day but really I'm just
going to come back to saying the
pointers are just integers which store a
memory address that is all that they are
get that into your head I'm going to be
making a lot more videos on this topic
and dealing with things like pointer
arithmetic and more advanced kind of
pointer operations so if you're new to
this channel feel free to subscribe as
you begin to use pointers and as we
begin to use pointers throughout this
series you'll get a lot more examples
and you'll see just how powerful they
are and what we can do with them but
this is the gist of how they work don't
overthink it they're really simple
thanks for watching and I hope you
enjoyed this video if you did please hit
that like button you can also follow me
on Twitter and Instagram and if you
really enjoyed this video and you want
to see more videos like this you can
support me on patreon.com theurn next
time we're going to be talking about
references and I'll see you guys in the
next video goodbye
[Music]